welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay
welcome to the stoah I'm the Stewart of
the stoah the stola has a place for us
to cohere and dialogue but what matters
most at the knife's edge of this moment
and we're very lucky to have Robin
Hanson back at the stove and he's going
to talk about a short blog piece he did
that was a called the contrary in moment
or the contrary in times something along
those lines so he's gonna share his
thoughts rushed contrarians yes that's
it so he's gonna share his thoughts on
that maybe contrarian ism in general and
then I'll warm him up with some
questions and then if you have a
question for Robin just write in the
chat box and then I will unmute you and
you can ask it to him yourself
that being said I'll hand it over to you
brother oh what a tall so I've been a
contrary in some sense most of my life
in my sort of personal style and I've
often reflected on the nature of
contrary anism and and how it relates to
people who aren't contrarian so a couple
of obvious facts you know most
institutions are run by people and
whatever view they have is not
considered contrary contrary in it the
the usual view is identified with the
view of authorities there's authorities
in charge or something then whatever
they say by definition isn't contrary so
contrary and is a in some sense a status
for a little thing not just popularity
if most people believed one thing but
the authorities believed another the
thing most people believed would
probably be considered contrary so most
say people in charge of things
try not to be visibly advised by
outsiders they they consider that to be
a challenge to their status that is if
it looks like you're being influenced by
people in some sense your status is
being lowered and there's this being
raised so high status people try not to
be visibly influenced if they're
influenced they try to do it privately
to private advisers things like that and
so when there's a wide public
conversation and there are contrarians
talking
going saying something against whatever
the authority the authority view would
be then in some sense they are seen as a
challenge to the authority they are
challenging the status of that authority
and sometimes of course the authorities
do badly and then their power is lost
and in part that happens because people
challenge them and people who are
looking to rise in status often will
take a moment to challenge a leader or
an authority as the moment to make their
bid because if they succeed in
persuading people of their challenge and
that the authorities are wrong and this
Challenger is right they may well decide
to replace the current authorities with
the new challenges so people are in
general framing opinions in this way not
just who's right who's wrong but whose
high status whose low status and our
willing authorities be dumped out of the
role or will they stay in that role and
are the challengers people who are
disagreeing with them publicly are those
people to consider as people to replace
them and that's just part of the general
dynamic of challenging an authority now
one key fact is that usually when
challengers disagree with authorities
it's hard to prove them right usually
they say something and you know the
world doesn't believe us some hard to
see and whatever claims you're making
goes to take a long time to be proven so
and usually authorities look magnanimous
and generous and authoritative if they
allow some degree of contrary and
criticism and disagree if you to quickly
squelch disagreement that seems you know
like you're showing that you already
said you're insecure you and maybe
you've got something to hide and maybe
those people have something to say that
you're trying to sponsor so in general
most times authorities want to give the
appearance of listening to criticism and
they do of course us into presidents a
lot but they don't want to seem to be
too visibly following any particular
rivals who might replace them and they
are usually somewhat safe from the sense
that in the usual noise in the world and
slow way to change that you can't really
see if the critics are right or not so
usually most people are going to presume
the authorities right the authorities
are willing to accept that so they're
willing to allow some criticism
and a small rate at which the
authorities seem wrong is okay as long
as usually people perceive and judge the
authorities right in a crisis like now
like a big war or pandemic these
dynamics change in interesting ways and
that allows us most to think about this
crisis and to think about the nature of
being a contrary so the most obvious
thing is that in a crisis like this
whatever you say that might be contrary
to what the authorities say you and the
authorities will be proven right or
wrong pretty fast and in a pretty
dramatic visible way so that means if
you're a contrary you might say ooh this
is my chance to prove myself I'm gonna
go out there and you know work on this
and figure out a contrarian thing to say
challenge the authorities and then I'll
be proven right and this will be my big
chance to shine yeah me yes and of
course you playing a pro-social you are
helping us all by China you know
checking the authorities and wondering
whether they're really right and trying
to help us all deal with problem but
think about this from the point of view
of the authorities usually they're
pretty safe in allowing contrarians to
you know challenge them and say things
and you know don't have to repress them
too much but now in a crisis well they
are more risk first of all there are
more at risk of people being unhappy
what they do because in a crisis that
stuff happens and you can blame the
authorities and worse that these
contrarians who complain about what
you're doing early on they could be more
easily proven right and that's a threat
to you as authorities so what do you do
well it seems more obvious you you want
to be less tolerant of contrarians
less hollering of challengers you more
what to you know circle the wagons you
know draw the line saying we're the
authorities those people are our
outsiders and if you have the resources
and most people will defer to you most
people will consider you by default to
be the right party and you can accuse
the other party of trying to you know
take away our unity that we need now in
this crucial time we need everybody to
be behind the common policy that we've
all chosen and those people are
challenging that and they are breaking
up our unity
and that's of course something we see
today I'll last leave you with the
example of world war one so leading up
to World War one there were a lot of
people who were anti-war a lot of people
visibly said you know war is bad
supporting your country's war that's not
good thing as soon as World War one
started those people showed up for a
couple years they completely shut up and
wisely suffering because people were
just completely intolerant they did not
let me hear that all these people who
are not so sure they like more all the
sudden people were too really eager for
war the nations all said yes gonna have
war our troops we held Christmas there
was this huge sense that everybody
should be behind that message nobody
should be questioning it and of course
even the United States
these are Sarpy key examples of where
the government requests free speech
basically by rounding on people who
disagreed with the war and throwing you
in jail for no other reason that they
had just agree with the war as an
example of how in a time of crisis
people tend to wanna you know back the
authorities support the authorities and
the authorities will be less tolerated
contraries anyway that was those are my
observations and let's talk cool so if
you have questions for Robin just write
it in chat box if you'd like me to read
it on your behalf just indicate that say
I'll warm you up with a few questions
and I'll roam the room up so what
compels you to be a contrarian expect
it's a personality text thing but you
could give a theory that you know
sometime in life you made a bid for
authority and or rejected and you framed
yourself as in this country with already
success I won't just support the
authorities and they'll support me and I
will be promoted up the usual ladder if
I play ball and do what I'm told some
time early on you got the signal that
was gonna work for you and so you
decided let me take this alternative you
know there's a lot of theories like that
in terms of personality types and roles
in society even say the standard story
of the first war enrich the claybournes
the firstborn tends to take the
authority role in the family of doing
with parents say it supporting parenting
roles and obedience and that sort of
thing later borns tend to be more of the
rebels
say well I didn't get to be firstborn by
somebody else right and in your book
elephant in the brain you talk a lot
about signaling and I'm curious like if
there's different shades of contrarians
signaling as I imagine some are just
sort of like into that quick hit of
showing people how smart you are and
other ones maybe come from more deeper
place this probably range I haven't
thought that much about it but obviously
one thing is just to show that you're
clever so often even specially in
philosophy you know if everybody has a
state review you can show your clever by
arguing for an alternative you I mean
many of the most impressive philosophers
or people who argue reviews they're
basically sound crazy even on reflection
but damn if they didn't have an
oppressive argument for you couldn't
immediately dismiss and you know if
you're trying to be impressive putting
together impressive argument for
something everybody thinks it's wrong is
a lot more aggressive then putting
together in a persuasive argument for
something everybody thinks it's right so
that's just one way to look impressive
then of course as I said there's this
defiance rebel rebel mode where you're
basically you know the old James II
quote what do you what do you against
what do you got basically the
disagreement is merely a signal that I
want a rebel rebel and I want to throw
out the incumbent and I want to take
their places you have to come up with an
excuse you come up with some reason but
that's not where your heart is your or
your focuses you just lerner about great
and to quote that's coming up is that
Hunter H Thompson who's like the problem
saying his name wrong but like when the
going gets weird the weird turns pro
right this is like and these kind of
weird visit of states you you want to
listen to the weirdness yeah so uh I
mean it's also Pro so I mean another
consideration is just flexibility that
is most people and I wrote another blog
post about this later bait most people
in their roles in the 30s in stable
parts of society they get used to a
state standard pattern and way things
are and then in a crisis that's a moment
of disruption reflects ability a
generality is more valuable and so
that's often what contrarians how
they're the polymath there
who stand ready to reason about a wide
range of things but aren't authorities
within a very narrow area right right
what's coming to mind - it's like if you
weren't successful in the right way in
the old world it's like almost does you
a service and the whole service to be
successful in sort of a potential new
world right crises seem that way
openings to people who are lower in
status who think they deserve to be
higher when I sort of displace the
existing Howard's the beat a crisis
often looks attracted to them exactly on
the other side people in power exactly
fear that and so they're gonna be more
protective right so I ask one more
question and we'll open up to the room
so who what contrarians do you love to
read and follow and listen to I I don't
have a set list like that but I have a
lot of people most of my friends are
kind of contrarian style and so I just
know a lot of people who are more
contrarian style and more generalist and
more calling that style right the
diverse many people in history a lot of
people who became like a successful
Authority what want to look back and
tell the story that they were that's
people say well used to be this
Authority then I came along and I I and
then we fought for a while and now I'm
in charge because we were right there
and so in our world today that origin
story of rebellion and contrariness is
one many people like but it's actually
not as true as people say a lot of
people who are authorities today we're
pretty much tony's before they found a
way to spin it as being a cool cool so
your videos a little bit blurry we can
hear you fine i don't know if you want
to turn it on turn it back on to see if
it works better supposed to happen now
so Amy would you like to read you a
question oh I think I have to allow you
to mute yourself okay go ahead Amy you
can unmute yourself now hi Robin how you
doing I had one question which is
basically what do you think that an
example of thoughtful practical
intelligent contrary anism
looks like in this time period it could
be a real example or an imagined it and
and excuse me an example and of course
the reason they're usually not possible
is most people can't tell the difference
the difference of being thoughtful is
that you are correct and careful rather
than incorrect islami and motivated and
most people again can't tell the
difference and so most people pretend to
be thoughtful so the obvious way to
actually be intelligent and thoughtful
is to think and to in addition to
whatever urge you have to be contrary
and actually be correct that's of course
a lot more work and it means you have to
sit through a lot more possibilities
before you find one that works the
thoughtless country more grabs one thing
right from the start and says that looks
good and runs with it the thoughtful
contrary you'll have sister 20 maybe 50
different contrary impossibilities in
each one go no that doesn't work that's
not right and eventually you come up
with one you say then you go that makes
sense Amy do you want to follow up
attender yes all right yeah I'm just
wondering if you have any practical
examples for this time period of what on
thoughtful contrarian ISM might look
like or does look like again that's just
the people I think are correct there's
nothing more subtle about it than people
who are you
I mean certainly when there are these
locked in dogmas people who even
question the dogmas are being a little
more thoughtful of course they may have
other motives for that but you know the
elites locked in pretty early to this
plan that we're all going to lock down
and stay there until we get a vaccine
and a lot of people said you can't stay
down that long a lot of people yes we
can because we're gonna have enough
tests we're gonna hire more you know
other things and the other you got to be
hopeful you got to believe and tech will
save us and a lot of people were going
what you sure but you know how does that
how does that work so a lot of people
saying yes but we need the whole
community to be behind the message and
behind the plan that we all have which
is to lock down as long as we need to
and you know that that's sort of a
saying is undermining our unity so uh
then you have a question hi hi there can
you hear me yep John oh great yeah so uh
yeah my my question I suppose was yet
kind of really about the value I guess
of of contrarians um and I was sort of
really struck I guess by what you were
saying you know about the the this sort
of the tension almost between those in
authority and then this notion of this
contrarian so I suppose my question
really was you know colonel do
contrarians
lead and I mean maybe this as a contrary
thing to say in itself but even if not
necessarily from the front as it were so
so that notion of of value and
[Music]
leadership and thought leadership and
social leadership and bind up with our
whole notion of being contrarian what's
your thoughts on well certainly again
many contrarians like to present
themselves I mean many leaders and
authorities like to present themselves
contrary you know so for example
scientific Authority often wants to
emphasize how it's different from that
old religious authority from forcing
how they were billed against that I
remember their rebellion way back then
where those rebels still and like in the
political world often a rebel political
movement will be co-opted by the
established political parties so you you
might you will win the election but the
established parties will say I guess
that seems to be popular let's adopt
those views and that similarly happens
in other environments a rebel company
and firms they might have a rebel
product and the established companies
like Apple or Google manages to squash
it but they decide well we're going to
copy this ideas that looks good and they
do and so in that sense contrarians lead
even if they don't become authorities
they they tell or ities that there's a
set of options that they should consider
and they co-op it and of course you know
Koreans do sometimes women and become
leaders but then there are no longer in
some sense by definition contrarians
because people see the Maoist into
authority but they still celebrate that
contrary in origin as legitimizing their
artillery okay thank you fine okay
Jordan you had a question hey Robin okay
so I've been following this guy courtesy
Arvind recently who talks a lot about
contrary anism and he has this idea that
you that there's like a this kind of
group consensus that we work in that
sort of a like a two-party two-story
system but that there's a there's like a
secret third story which is a kind of a
stereotype of what it looks like to be a
contrarian like for example in America's
kind of like the founding myth of the
the current system is partially embedded
in like an opposition to Nazism so
there's this stereotype about
contrarians that they look like Nazis
that but the problem with it is that
like you people who are contrary and
oftentimes find themselves drawn to
these stereotypes and they start doing
habit them accidentally without
realizing that like
that the fact that they're behaving that
way is just because they're inhabiting
just like the third part of the
territory and so you end up with people
in Charlottesville and this kind of
stuff in the question is later is that
their genuine belief or are they are
they kind of like misfiring on a
contrary an impulse and then doing so in
a way that like highlights them as a
target which is like beneficial to the
system so I wonder if you've heard these
ideas before if you don't like for
example my cult xcode blogger eliezer
yudkowsky years ago talked about how you
know the stereotypical young teenage
rebel all looks and dresses and talks
the same they're rebelling against some
larger world but they are conforming to
a sub world and you know in many ways
when we feel like rebelling or being
amount of informants we don't try to
sort of just go out and be personally
distinctive we often look for a model
and try to join in that model so and
that of course can reinforce you know so
for example today many contrarians think
that they should not be polite or
careful in their speech or logical in
their analysis they think they should
defy that that yell and be rude and call
people names and draw rude pictures
because you know that's their idea a lot
of contrary it is like it's it's those
Tonys who are polite and careful and
gracious and you know acknowledge the
points of others and things like that
whereas it's true rebels who know that's
all needs to be rejected right so you
know like in general you know it's very
hard to escape you know identifying with
something or rebelling against it and
doing the opposite and of course in some
sense you're just as conformist if you
try to be the opposite of something that
if you try to be exactly the same is it
the hard part is to be thoughtful about
well what exactly makes sense what else
but most likely if you are that kind of
thoughtful contrary and you won't be
near other people in the space of
behaviors or styles or positions
and you won't be part of a little bit
people really create being part of so
yes but of course the contrarians
conformism isn't any worse than the
conformist confinement you know status
quo conformist conformism it's just a
different style and in both of them of
course play roles Narayan I'm realizing
like in my own life that sometimes I
play the role of contrarian and other
times I play the role of like looking
for people who appear to be contrarians
and trying to evaluate whether or not
like what kind of value that they
actually hold and I was thinking that
like it seems like what you're saying is
that the first most important part is to
be right and if you're right and
everyone else is wrong that's when you
become that valuable contrarian that can
shift the masses to being more right but
if you're right but you're also with
everyone else you still need to have the
discernment to figure out is that person
the contrary and are they corrected
should I update towards them so I was
thinking about like the stock markets
and how they seemed to incentivize
contrarian to are right I'm curious if
you have any thoughts about how society
as a whole might be restructured to
actually incentivize contrarians who are
correct I've actually spent a big part
of my career thinking about that so you
know basically the stock market is like
betting markets in the same structure
called speculative markets and they do
in fact give people strong incentives to
just be accurate not to be thrower
against some trend but just yeah and we
can show that we have very good data
over time that shows across a very wide
range of topics we can just be more
accurate together if we